Guide to the Charlotte B. DeForest Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Charlotte B. DeForest Papers
1879-1967
RG 178
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material in the Charlotte B. DeForest Papers document her work in women's higher education in Japan, her literary efforts to translate Japanese poetry and children's books, and her work with Japanese-Americans. Charlotte Burgis DeForest was the daughter of ABCFM missionaries to Japan and a graduate of Smith College. She was a missionary educator in Japan from 1903 to 1940, serving on the faculty and as president of Kobe College. During World War II she was involved in work with Japanese-American detainees.
DeForest, Charlotte B., 1879-
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received from UCBWM offices.
Biographical / Historical
1879 Feb 23 Charlotte Burgis DeForest was born in Osaka, Japan, daughter of ABCFM missionaries Elizabeth Starr and John Hyde DeForest, who served in Japan from 1874 to their respective deaths in 1915 and ca. 1910. Charlotte's sister Lydia and her husband William B. Pettus were missionaries to China serving under the YMCA.
1882-1883 In America on furlough with parents
1894 Feb-May In private boarding school in Hanover, Germany
1894-1897 Attended, graduated from Newton High School, Newtonville, MA
1897-1901 B.A., Smith College
1902 Sep -1903 Aug Assistant superintendent of Missionary Home, Auburndale, MA
1903Dec Returned to Japan as missionary serving under American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
1904 Language study in Sendai
1905 Taught English at Kobe College, with time for language study
1906Apr-1907 Mar Traveling to visit schools; language study
1907 Apr Returned to Kobe College: In charge of Sunday School work and later appointed as head of the Bible Department
1907 M.A., Smith College
1910-1911 Oct Acting Principal of Kobe College during absence of Miss Searle
1911Nov -1913 On leave of absence
1912Mar-May Studied at Hartford School of Missions
1913 Returned to teaching at Kobe: English, Bible, Music
1915 Appointed President of Kobe by Woman's Board of Missions of the Interior
1920 Studied at University of Chicago
1921 L.H.D. degree from Smith College
1921-1925 At Kobe
1925 Dec - 1926 Dec Business trip and health leave in U.S.
1929 - 1934 On Doshisha University Board of Trustees
1935Jun -1936 On furlough in U.S. and Europe
1939 Received medal from Hyogo Prefectural Education Association
1940 Resigned presidency of Kobe; named "Honorary President"; received various citations and medals from Japanese government
1941- 1943 Worked part time in American Board Library
1942 -1943 Volunteer work for Japanese detainees at Boston Immigration Station
1943-1944 Taught nine month course in Japanese language to Army Student Training Unit at Pomona College, Claremont, CA
1944 Jun - 1945 Dec Worked as "junior counselor" in Social Welfare Department of the U.S. government at Manzanar, CA Relocation Center for Japanese evacuees from West Coast (e.g., for military hearings)
1947 Returned to Kobe College to teach and help rally alumnae
1950 On leaving Japan, receive Fourth Grade of the Order of the Sacred Treasure
1951 Retired at Pilgrim Place, Claremont, CA
1960 Invited by alumnae to attend 85th anniversary of Kobe College
Scope and Contents
Series I, Correspondence, begins with letters written by Charlotte to her parents as she left them in Japan and began her journey to continue her education first in Germany and then in the United States. Charlotte had literary interests and wrote substantive, detailed letters throughout her life. Charlotte's letters to family members dating from 1907 to 1912 are primarily from Japan, except when she was on furlough or vacationing in Kuling, China. Circular letters written by Charlotte date from 1940 to 1951 and relate primarily to her activities at Kobe College. Also of interest in Series I are letters written to Charlotte by Kobe College alumnae who were affected by the relocation of Japanese-Americans during World War II.
Series II, Writings, provide valuable autobiographical information about Charlotte DeForest, as well her writings on a variety of Japan-related topics. Journals kept by Charlotte in Japan, when she was eleven to fourteen years old (1890-1893), provide fascinating detailed information regarding the activities and feelings of a missionary child of the era. The later diaries are of the five-year variety.
Series III, Subject Files, includes material related to Kobe College and several files relating to Charlotte's translation and publication projects. She worked with Japanese writer Tasuku Harada, who was pastor of the Kobe Kumiai Church and later president of Doshisha University of Kyoto, to versify Japanese nursery rhymes that Harada had translated into English. Correspondence and drafts relate to the publication of The Prancing Pony: Nursery Rhymes from Japan.
Series IV, Personal Items and Memorabilia, includes biographical information, photographs of Charlotte DeForest and Kobe College, and collected memorabilia. One folder of correspondence in this series relates to Charlotte's inquiries regarding familial history of the incidence of cleft (or hare) lips. The folder of biographical information regarding Charlotte's brother John includes genealogical information about the DeForest family.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Subject Files
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia
Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Missions -- Japan; Missionaries; DeForest, Charlotte B., 1879-; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions -- Missions -- Japan; Kōbe Jogakuin
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Letters to parents, 1893 Nov- 1909 Dec (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
  - Letters to mother and sisters, 1911 May - 1915 Feb (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Letters to sisters, 1907 Mar - 1912 Apr (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to sisters, 1942 Aug - 1950 Mar (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
  - Letters to nieces and nephews, 1964 Aug- 1965 Oct (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters to "Robins", 1940 Aug - 1942 Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Circular letters, 1940 - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters related to Kobe College, incl. to/from Presidents Monkichi Namba and Tetsutaro Ariga, 1946-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Misc. incomplete letters (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters from parents, 1887-1900 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters to/from others: A - K (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Letters to/from others: L - W (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Letters of John DeForest, 1879 May, 1886 Oct (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letters of Kobe College alumnae affected by Japanese relocation during World War II, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Address lists (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Writings, Series II
  - Memoirs, journal entries, "How My Mother Brought Me Up," "The Span of My Life" (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Pets in the Bible," "The Double Verilys in John's Gospel," "Why I Believe in Prayer" (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "My Friend Mr. Nagata," "Rambles in Owani," Chinese dialogue, others (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Thesis for M.A. degree: "Some Types of Japanese Poetry" (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "Susie's Angels," "Who Interpreted for Commodore Perry," "Some Thoughts on Japanese Childrens' Songs" (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Am I My Brother's Keeper?," "Woman's Progress in Japan," "Discipline That Saves Face" (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Poems Down the Years" (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Journals, 1890 Jun -1893 Dec (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Diaries, 1933, 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Writings of Others (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Subject Files, Series III
  - Kobe College: General information (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
  - Kobe College: 75th and 85th anniversaries, including photo album, 1950, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Translation of "The Prancing Pony": Correspondence and drafts, 1910-1967 (Box 3, Folder 42-44)
  - Translations: "A Japanese Doctor Visits Schweitzer", 1965 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Translations: "The Nadachi Landslide", 1937 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Translations: "Light is Here", 1951 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Translations: Assorted poems and stories (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Material re. literature on /of Japan (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous news clippings re. Japan (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Open letter to the World YMCA from Japan YMCA concerning Hydrogen Bomb experiments in the Pacific, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 50a)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series IV
  - News clippings about C DeF, 1935-1956 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Awards and citations, 1907-1961 (Box 4, Folder 52-52a)
  - Smith College (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Biographical records (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Biographical information on brother, John DeForest (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Letters researching cleft palate and hare lip (condition occurring among various family members) (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Japanese crafts and culture (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Programs and collected items (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Gift booklets - greetings and sketches (Box 4, Folder 59-60)
  - Photos of C DeF (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Photo album - Tokyo visit, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Photo album - 85th anniversary of Kobe College, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 64)